Abraham: What exactly is threat modelling?
Nicole: Threat modelling is an
overall risk-based approach to
identify and resolve any potential
threats and vulnerabilities that may
compromise a business or organisation.
Abraham: There are many different
threat models and many different
frameworks involved but they all
follow similar steps and have the
same goal in preparing an organisation
or business on what might happen if
they fall prey to malicious attacks.
By proactively anticipating scenarios
that may impact an organisation they also
give an opportunity to look at what might
possibly happen even in extremes cases.
Nicole: At the beginning of the
process, it is important to plan what
framework is needed for the threat model
and who and what it needs to cover.
So, let’s look at an overall view of
the stages involved in threat modelling.
The Discovery stage identifies
any desirable assets, any attack
vectors or threats surrounding them,
and how hackers may reach them.
Abraham: The Implementation stage,
uses and analyses information
gathered in the discovery stage.
This may be looking at potential
impact and how to prioritise the most
damaging attacks, and how to resolve the
vulnerabilities associated with these.
Let’s look at these stages in more
detail starting with the discovery stage.
Nicole: All assets including data and
applications should be catalogued.
This could be business assets, the
various data components and applications
that are necessary to run a business
and if targeted could disrupt the
activities of an organisation or business.
It could also be data assets which could
be crypto mined to sell on the dark web.
Abraham: Hackers are often opportunists
who look for easiest way in to exploit
already-known vulnerabilities, using tried
and tested routes such as unprotected
admin accounts and default passwords.
The areas at risk that hold the
data are the attack surface.
By mapping out all the components
of these areas that communicate with
the asset, threat modelling teams
can see how data flows to and from
the asset and any potential risks.
Nicole: Identify the paths that
hackers use to reach these areas from
system penetration to asset removal.
Hackers may have multiple ways to exploit
paths so these should be analysed also.
This can be done by collecting
information on known exploits and
vulnerabilities that relate to each path.
Abraham: This is where the good
actors or white hat hackers come in.
Thinking like a hacker makes
it easier to stop an attack
by being prepared and secure.
So, we have looked at the discovery
stage, now let’s look at the
implementation stage in more detail.
Nicole: The implementation stage
of threat modelling begins with a
comprehensive analysis of previously
gather discovery stage information.
Analysis of information collected
should be used to assess the
potential impact for each attack type.
This should be done using any
assumptions made and any threat
intelligence or indicators.
As an attack can cause a chain of events
it’s important that the analysis covers
as much potential damage as possible.
This may include reputation, leaked
data, legal action, general costs
to put things right such as relacing
equipment and the downtime that may
be caused of organisational services.
Abraham: Prioritisation is one of the
last steps of threat modelling which
prioritises previously discovered
vulnerabilities by focussing on the
most dangerous high impact attacks.
Once these have been addressed then
a hierarchy would be followed to
address the ‘less’ important threats.
The final step is finding security
controls to mitigate all vulnerabilities
and remove and counter any threats.
It is also the time when any
security gaps not discovered in
the initial stage can be addressed.
Nicole: Threat modelling is important to
all businesses and organisations although
it can be costly and time consuming.
It is often done manually by a competent
cyber security team but can also be
automated by using threat modelling
tools for those who don’t have a range
of cybersecurity personnel available.
Abraham: How do we
evaluate a threat model?
Nicole: Each threat model has
its own specific process and
sometimes threat models are used
in conjunction with each other.
Some focus on valuable assets, some more
on the types of attack, some on who uses
the system and some on prioritising.
But whichever model is chosen it
should meet the purpose and needs of
the organisation or business and the
strengths of their cyber security
team, and when it comes down to it,
a lot depends on what the business is
or what the organisation does to help
with the evaluation of suitability.